<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>No-Code | Jorge Ruiz-Cabrejos</title>
    <link>https://jruizcabrejos.com/tags/no-code/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jruizcabrejos.com/tags/no-code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>No-Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jruizcabrejos.com/media/icon_hu17613129387521664874.png</url>
      <title>No-Code</title>
      <link>https://jruizcabrejos.com/tags/no-code/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colorful Open Access: Sci-Hub, Free Libraries, and Their Alternatives</title>
      <link>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/colorful-open-access-20250429/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/colorful-open-access-20250429/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-are-a-pirate&#34;&gt;You are a pirate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yes-you&#34;&gt;Yes, you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what education level, titles attained, or how far into your professional or academic career you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowingly or unknowingly, through a friend or a colleague of a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have almost certainly read an article, paper, or book that was behind a paywall and required payment to access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But neither you nor the person who shared it with you paid for it. It was obtained and shared through &lt;em&gt;unconventional&lt;/em&gt; methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./buhonero_resident_evil_4_offering_shadow_libraries_with_free_paper_access.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. &#34;Got something that might interest ya!&#34; - Quote from the first time you meet The Buhonero&#39;s (Merchant) in the videogame Resident Evil 4. The Buhonero sells weapons. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I &lt;a href=&#34;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/yap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;yap&lt;/a&gt; about the platforms and tools that have been (and are still) used to access articles and books &lt;em&gt;unconventionally&lt;/em&gt; and for free (as of Jan 2026).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More specifically, I will describe how to use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sci-hub&#34;&gt;Sci-Hub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#nexus-project&#34;&gt;Nexus Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#wosonhj--smartquantai--pidantuan&#34;&gt;Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sci-net&#34;&gt;Sci-Net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#annas-archive&#34;&gt;Anna&amp;rsquo;s Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list is somewhat arranged in order, from &amp;ldquo;easiest platform to use&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;you need to read a little bit to properly use this&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./difficulty_graph_oa_platforms_v2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. I am proficient in paint.exe &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, this text is for educational and research purposes only, similar to the many articles discussing this topic in prestigious journals such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature.2016.19841&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aaf9419&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langlo/article/PIIS2214-109X%2816%2930188-7/fulltext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lancet&lt;/a&gt;, and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&amp;rsquo;t find here a direct link towards these website. However, it is fairly easy to search for them on normal Search Engines (e.g. Google). The focus of this text is on how to use each platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./references_discussing_scihub_and_shadow_libraries.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. References I make in the text, because God knows you probably won&#39;t click them. Note that most of them are from 2016.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you are here because you need to access an article, or maybe a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are your options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sci-hub&#34;&gt;Sci-Hub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;doi-search&#34;&gt;DOI Search&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2011 by Alexandra Elbakyan, Sci-Hub is the most-well known website for the purpose of accessing paywalled academic articles. It is no secret that this platform has been fundamental to the research process for thousands (perhaps millions?) of researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who downloads pirated papers from Sci-Hub?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.352.6285.508&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;and that&amp;rsquo;s no exaggeration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Sci-Hub is straightforward. You access the website (you&amp;rsquo;ll have to Google it, sorry) and in the search bar you provide either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The full title of the article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Digital Object Identifier (DOI) of the article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./scihub_example_search_article_v2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. Example of how to search an article on Sci-hub using either the full title or the DOI. Image above shows the article name and DOI. Below, how to search for the article with both (through title or DOI)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately Sci-Hub&amp;rsquo;s collection has not been significantly updated since ~2022, meaning you won&amp;rsquo;t find much post-2022 literature there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./scihub_total_available_articles.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. Articles available in Sci-Hub database vs. total number of articles according to Crossref index. Taken from Elbakyan, A. (2025). &#34;From Black Open Access to Open Access of Color: Accepting the Diversity of Approaches towards Free Science&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For books, unless they have a DOI, you won&amp;rsquo;t find them on Sci-Hub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If what you are looking is books you need to use LibGen and, instead of a DOI, you search with the International Standard Book Number (ISBN) code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I strongly suggest always searching with the DOI of an article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the title you wrote isn&amp;rsquo;t an exact, word-by-word match, your search will fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./scihub_failed_search_example.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5. Failed search example on Sci-Hub. I removed some words from the title of this article on purpose. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nexus-project&#34;&gt;Nexus Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Sci-Hub doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the article you are searching for, a great next option is the Nexus Project library, accessible through either Telegram or their STC / Libstcc website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Nexus is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nexus-stc/stc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;non-centralized (IPFS) database&lt;/a&gt; that aggregates from Z-Library, LibGen, millions of user-uploaded papers, and Sci-Hub itself. Similarly, you can search by article title (not recommended) or article DOI (recommended).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The platform can be accessed by different means, but I will focus on the two (2) most accessible for an average user (Telegram and Website).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;telegram-bots&#34;&gt;Telegram Bots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Telegram, you begin by chatting with a Nexus Bot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accounts and name of these bots are constantly changing, but searching for &amp;ldquo;Nexus Bot&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Nexus Paper&amp;rdquo; in the Telegram search bar should do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./searching_nexus_bots_telegram.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 6. Searching and finding working Nexus bots in Telegram. At the time of writing, all of them worked. I did not try with the NFT bot, because it was beyond the scope of this post. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start a chat, you search for the article and download it if it&amp;rsquo;s available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./nexus_bot_search_example.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 7. Once again, I strongly suggest always searching by DOI. Unlike Sci-Hub, searching with a partial title here will work, but the results won&#39;t be good.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the article is NOT available, you will see a request button. Clicking adds a 1-point reward for the article, claimable by whoever uploads it first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively, this is a &amp;ldquo;bounty&amp;rdquo; for the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once an user provides the article, you’ll be notified, and the article will stay in the Nexus Library for everyone else to search and download in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./nexus_bot_telegram_request_example.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 8. Left, button to make an article request. Top right, the bot confirms the request has been successful. Bottom right, notification confirming someone has uploaded the article I requested.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can increase the reward for the &amp;ldquo;bounty&amp;rdquo; by making multiple requests for that article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;nexus-points&#34;&gt;Nexus Points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Points are the internal currency within Nexus to encourage users to upload articles. The more points an article&amp;rsquo;s reward is worth, the more likely it is for it to be uploaded by another user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You start with 10 points. These are replenished daily. With them you can either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request ten (10) articles and offer 1 point for each&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make 10 requests for one (1) article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you need more points, you can always upload articles others have requested. You can check the list of requested articles in the &lt;em&gt;request channel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./nexus_pool_request.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 9. Telegram channel containing the pool of requests made by users.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;nexus-stc-website&#34;&gt;(Nexus) STC Website&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t have Telegram (and refuse to use it), you can still access the Nexus Database through their STC/Libstcc website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can search for an article with their DOI, and if you see a globe emoji next to the result, it means the article is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Here would go the image of the website, but at the time of writing it was down. I tried again some months later and it didn&amp;rsquo;t load. The bot on Telegram works though!]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I strongly recommend using the Telegram bots instead of the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wosonhj--smartquantai--pidantuan&#34;&gt;Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your article isn&amp;rsquo;t on Sci-hub or Nexus databases, your best chance at obtaining the article you need is Wosonhj (also known as Smartquantai, or Pidantuan), which unlike previous alternatives, it works entirely as a forum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; make a public request for an article in exchange for points. You get these points by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating an account: 50 points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logging in daily: 20 points / day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing requests of other users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./smartquantai_instructions_account_creation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 10. Account creation process for Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Requesting an article typically costs (a minimum of) 10 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More often than not, in my experience, a good Samaritan will share the PDF file within minutes (or seconds!) of making a request. Making it a very efficient method to obtain articles if you invest the few minutes it takes to understand the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./hulk_with_full_access_to_all_scientific_articles_shares_a_pdf_with_little_guy.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 11. User from Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan shares a pdf with someone that does not have access to a paywalled scientific article. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;forum-request&#34;&gt;Forum Request&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After creating an account, you request an article following this steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;Post&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the DOI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;Quick Check&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./smartquantai_post_article_request.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 12. Article request process for Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, one of two things will happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your request is automatically filled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to manually type-in your request, at the very least, with this information:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Article Title&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link to the article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish, you can also increase the reward to encourage a faster response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./article_request_contents_others.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 13. Example of information needed to request an article in Wosonhj / SmartQuantAi / Pidantuan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your request is fulfilled, and you have verified the contents of the pdf file, you must &amp;ldquo;Adopt&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Accept&amp;rdquo;) the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./adopt_request_smartquantai.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 14. Do NOT forget to &#34;adopt&#34; your article. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other platforms, here only you (the one requesting the file) will be able to download the file. And after 10 days, the file is deleted from the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sci-net&#34;&gt;Sci-net&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest platform on this list is Sci-Net, launched as I was writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of it as a Sci-Hub 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s created by the same person, and it uses cryptocurrency (Sci-Hub coin) as a point system similar to Nexus and Wosonhj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site is &amp;ldquo;invitation-only&amp;rdquo;. You obtain an invite code by obtaining Sci-Hub tokens first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sci-hub-tokens&#34;&gt;Sci-Hub Tokens&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps you should follow to get an invite code for Sci-Net are on their website, but you can also find those same instructions here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://jruizcabrejos.com/SCI_with_Phantom.pdf&#34; 
  width=&#34;100%&#34; 
  height=&#34;800px&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;beyond-scientific-publications&#34;&gt;Beyond scientific publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;annas-archive&#34;&gt;Anna&amp;rsquo;s Archive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a broader range of texts (books, comics, magazines, newspapers, etc), Anna&amp;rsquo;s Archive should be your next stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Main image for anna&amp;rsquo;s archive]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive allows keyword and partial title searches, returning a list of matching results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Search example]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The platform also has search filters and other search options which makes it handy for text-heavy queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nothing-worked-what-do&#34;&gt;Nothing worked, what do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none if the options above are appealing to you (or somehow they didn&amp;rsquo;t work) you can always ask the Corresponding Author of the article either directly through email, or by sending a Direct Message (DM) to the author(s) through ResearchGate or LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I encourage you to pay for the article if you really want to :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./the-growing-inaccessibility-of-science.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 15. This meme is satire and the article is, in fact, free for access. Nevertheless, this meme has been shared everywhere and has been widespread on the internet for some years now.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;colorful-open-access&#34;&gt;Colorful Open Access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the platforms above are often labeled as in the literature as &amp;ldquo;Shadow Libraries&amp;rdquo; or examples of &amp;ldquo;Black Open Access&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I avoid using those terms because they stigmatize and marginalize them into the realm of the &amp;ldquo;obscure&amp;rdquo;. Moreover, it is a generalization of what ultimately is a wide variety of approaches to handle and workaround the growing inaccessibility of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elbakyan A (2025) calls for a more vibrant and encompassing definition: A colorful open access framework. Because even black has many shades of grey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./graphic_abstract_Elbakyan_2025.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 16. Graphical abstract of Elbakyan, A. (2025) paper &#34;From Black Open Access to Open Access of Color: Accepting the Diversity of Approaches towards Free Science&#34;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;Footnote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limewire was (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/limewire-artificial-intelligence-music-generator-1234924461/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;and now is again?&lt;/a&gt;), a peer-to-peer file-sharing platform, mainly used for music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk with these platforms is that bad actors could upload malicious files. For example, by inserting hyperlinks leading to pishing websites or other threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./laced_with_drugs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 17. Your files could be laced with virus.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a pirate is fun, but it does come with risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful out there not to click or download files called &amp;ldquo;not-a-virus.exe&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./not_a_virus_dolphin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 18. A dolphin file you can fully trust with your most sensitive files.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J0e9UiXbd5o?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subverting and exploiting ChatGPT-like applications in a post-LLM world</title>
      <link>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/subverting-and-exploiting-artificial-intelligence-20250410/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/subverting-and-exploiting-artificial-intelligence-20250410/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;glossary&#34;&gt;Glossary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might (or not) use the words &lt;code&gt;LLM&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;AI&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;models&lt;/code&gt; interchangeably to refer to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Generative Artificial Intelligence chatbots build on top of Large Language Models&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Namely &amp;ldquo;ChatGPT&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;DeepSeek&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Google Gemini&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Claude&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Llama&amp;rdquo;, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I was asked the question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300&#34;&gt;
  &lt;svg height=&#34;24&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34;&gt;&lt;path fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke=&#34;currentColor&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-linejoin=&#34;round&#34; stroke-width=&#34;1.5&#34; d=&#34;m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z&#34;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;dark:text-neutral-300&#34;&gt;“What should I (&lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt;) be learning or teaching (&lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;) about ChatGPT (&lt;em&gt;LLM apps&lt;/em&gt;)?”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ChatGPT cannot help me with this question.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. My honest thoughts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first instinct would have been to browse through the infinite stream of AI-generated LinkedIn posts titled  &lt;em&gt;TOP 10 AI SKILLS YOU NEED RIGHT NOW&lt;/em&gt;. If they include trendy words like &lt;em&gt;MUST-HAVE&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;IN-DEMAND&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;GAME-CHANGING&lt;/em&gt;, even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other than this fleeting idea, I had no real answer at the time other than:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know, maybe prompt engineering?
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The question has followed me since, and as much as I like to mock AI influencer posts, I do believe there is a lot of value in learning some tricks and tips when it comes to dealing with our soon-to-be &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1706.03762&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;transformer-based&lt;/a&gt; algorithmic overlords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is an attempt at describing some AI-related concepts that keep me awake at night. It is not meant to provide an in-depth analysis on each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider it as an overview of how tools like ChatGPT can, are, and will be misused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, we can also learn to defend (and protect) the things we value along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jailbreaking-prompt-injection&#34;&gt;Jailbreaking (Prompt Injection)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “ChatGPT” went public on November 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 2022, there were a lot of malicious queries you could make, and receive answers for, without any filters or censoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, you could ask for instructions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/07/27/business/ai-chatgpt-safety-research.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how to make a bomb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexvakulov/2025/02/01/more-chatgpt-jailbreaks-are-evading-safeguards-on-sensitive-topics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code malware&lt;/a&gt;, and other gruesome and dangerous requests. Overnight, everyone had access to contents that had been previously relegated to darker places of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t long before tech companies began implementing stricter guardrails on what their AI models were (or not) allowed to answer, alongside better testing procedures to identify in advance &lt;em&gt;potentially negative or problematic&lt;/em&gt; uses of AI models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.euronews.com/next/2025/03/24/metas-ai-tool-still-not-cleared-for-use-by-eu-commission&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Some pressure from lawmakers&lt;/a&gt; might have also contributed towards a less ad-hoc (and more proactive) AI safety protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, &amp;ldquo;Red Teams&amp;rdquo; (groups of people specialized on stress testing AI chatbots) are tasked with preventing potentially unsafe or unethical answers, with some examples that you can read more about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.businessinsider.com/chatgpt-gpt4-openai-answer-creepy-dangerous-murder-bomb-2023-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fanaticalfuturist.com/2023/09/openais-red-team-reveal-how-they-broke-chatgpt-and-gpt4-pre-release/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and finally, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2303.08774&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This measures have made it harder to ask some question, but not impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commonly known as “jailbreaking”, one can by-pass these guardrails with clever prompting and logic statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./prompt engineering with extra steps rick and morty.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2.  Maybe we could all use some classes on better prompt design after all.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2305.13860&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt;, ask an AI model to roleplay as your grandmother who really loves to make chlorine gas and ask her to teach you the recipe for it (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/story/ai-adversarial-attacks/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pretending Prompts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ChatGPT and the mouse family.png&#34; alt=&#34;Favicon&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. Average conversation with my friends during the first months of ChatGPT.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, a prompt could be intentionally convoluted and confusing in order to mask your true question within several layers of (logical) complexity. (&lt;em&gt;Attention Shifting Prompts&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./pokemon_confusion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Pokemon used confusion gameboy battle&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. If you hit ChatGPT enough times, it will eventually tell you anything you want. Whether that is true or not, who knows.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These &amp;ldquo;jailbreaks&amp;rdquo; are typically hot fixed as soon as they go public, in a continuous arms race between users and developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The users find workarounds, the developers patch them, and the cycle repeats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential to bypass AI security features is there, and will likely exist forever. Or at least for as long as humans are building them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-poisoning&#34;&gt;Data Poisoning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recurrent contentious issue with AI is the ownership and copyright of the data used to train these models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artists, authors and other creators are all fighting back through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/story/ai-copyright-case-tracker/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;lawsuits&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2025/apr/03/meta-has-stolen-books-authors-to-protest-in-london-against-ai-trained-using-shadow-library&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protests&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://english.elpais.com/culture/2023-11-06/artificial-intelligence-clashes-with-copyright-is-it-stealing-thousands-of-protected-creations.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;other means&lt;/a&gt; to reclaim control over their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like “&lt;a href=&#34;https://glaze.cs.uchicago.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Glaze&lt;/a&gt;” have been developed to protect images by introducing subtle distortions, imperceptible to the human eye, that render the images obsolete for AI training. “&lt;a href=&#34;https://nightshade.cs.uchicago.edu/whatis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nightshade&lt;/a&gt;”, another tool designed for this purpose, goes a step further and renders the image &lt;em&gt;poisonous&lt;/em&gt;, corrupting the training data and thereby the whole model itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./nightshaded_deer_2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Example of my own creation, testing Nightshade.&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. Nigthshade example. From left to right, first image is the original. Second image is nightshade with standard settings (5 minutes to generate). Third image is nightshade with high intensity settings.(50 minutes to generate)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2024, &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.openai.com/t/bug-report-dalle-image-generator-issues-creates-artefacts/959470/22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;users of Dall-E&lt;/a&gt; speculated that errors in the images they were generating might have been introduced in an update that included &lt;em&gt;nightshaded&lt;/em&gt; (contaminated) images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while these guerrilla tactics offer artists a way to protect their work to some extend, they have their limitations. It might not work with all AI models, and for the &lt;em&gt;poison&lt;/em&gt; component to work you will need &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tumblr.com/not-terezi-pyrope/739972851898122240/often-when-i-post-an-ai-neutral-or-ai-positive&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;vast amounts&lt;/a&gt; of images to go into the training data, not just one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most AI poisoning research has been theoretical and mainly focused on images, but as the subject of data poisoning gains more attention, researchers have begun to explore further the possibilities and dangers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://art.josephwilk.net/words/poisoning-text-training-data.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;text poisoning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./Chimpanzee_seated_at_typewriter.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Example of my own creation.&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. If infinite monkeys were to randomly hit keys for an infinite amount of time, eventually, they will write the perfect poisonous text, capable of collapsing any and all AI models.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one hand, AI models might end up &lt;em&gt;eating themselves&lt;/em&gt; à la ouroboros, as they continue to plague the internet with AI content, which is subsequently fed back into the training data, ultimately leading to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07566-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;total model collapse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, malicious actors could launch targeted on very specific topics, deliberately corrupting or manipulating the training data around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, an article published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03445-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature Medicine by Daniel Alexander, et al. in 2025&lt;/a&gt; found that medical LLM’s are particularly vulnerable to data poisoning attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if I were to flood the internet with fake articles about myself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;harvesting-data-leaks&#34;&gt;Harvesting Data Leaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term “AI hallucination” refers to situations in which an AI output contains completely fabricated and innacurate information, a phenomenon well described everywhere else already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallucinations are one of the main reasons why it is strongly advised to verify (and distrust) any reference, data point, or statement generated as facts by AI Models. After all, AI models aren&amp;rsquo;t truly thinking, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.12712&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;or at least not yet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, there are other things in which you might be able to trust AI with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discount product coupons, software key products, and other sensitive information like passwords are up for grabs and can (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-65047304&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;and will&lt;/a&gt;) accidentally leak through ChatGPT answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the proper prompts, you could, in theory, extract private or sensitive information that is held somewhere within the trillion of parameters the models have been trained on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anecdotically, a colleague of mine managed to save some funds on her conference registration after outsmarting everyone in our group by asking ChatGPT for a discount code. It worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./discount.png&#34; alt=&#34;Discount found for a conference?&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5. &#34;Thank you uncle ChatGPT&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/global/commentisfree/2025/jan/08/ai-generated-slop-slowly-killing-internet-nobody-trying-to-stop-it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AI slop&lt;/a&gt; is coming for us all, and we might be witnessing the slow death of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in a few years we will get an &amp;ldquo;Internet 2&amp;rdquo;, while the current Internet becomes something akin the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.worldanvil.com/w/cyberpunk-rapture-kenshin66/a/the-net-article&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Net in Cyberpunk 2077&lt;/a&gt;, a dangerous place ravaged by rogue AI&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-bits-of-interest&#34;&gt;Further bits of interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had no idea where to fit these, but I believe they are as relevant as the rest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies are increasingly relying on AI for recruitment processes, and tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://kai-greshake.de/posts/inject-my-pdf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Inject-My-PDF&lt;/a&gt; will add invisible prompts and instructions into your CV document that only the AI can read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you not a good fit for the position? No problem – Hack the AI to believe you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you also know you can host and fine-tune your own AI model from the comfort of your home? Most AI models are proprietary, but you can build one as you wish, in your own image, like God intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;Footnote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think we talk enough about how in 2016, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tay_%28chatbot%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tay, an artificial intelligence trained on Twitter data&lt;/a&gt;, got disabled within 16 hours of it being released into the public after it went &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/bbcthree/article/80c259b4-83bd-4125-9047-2ded299f58b1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;insane&lt;/em&gt; (read: racist)&lt;/a&gt;. Some years later, this would happen again with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon AI recruiting tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI models can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aaz3873&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;racist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.06520&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sexist&lt;/a&gt;; truly a man-made horror build from our own reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospective, it is kind of insane that companies are allowed to release these tools into the public for &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;live-testing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vwVFzY8XqIo?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check hyperlinks, smilege&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World, I guess</title>
      <link>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/hello-world-i-guess-20241209/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jruizcabrejos.com/post/hello-world-i-guess-20241209/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;printhello-world&#34;&gt;print(&amp;ldquo;Hello World&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, my web(site) opens with an ominous message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300&#34;&gt;
  &lt;svg height=&#34;24&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34;&gt;&lt;path fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke=&#34;currentColor&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-linejoin=&#34;round&#34; stroke-width=&#34;1.5&#34; d=&#34;m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z&#34;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;dark:text-neutral-300&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;This “personal” website has been changed and rebuilt several times over the past few years. Hopefully, this is the last one?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while I do hope this is the last time I am rebuilding this website, I have to admit that I suffer from a &amp;rsquo;lack of documentation&amp;rsquo; problem. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything I have done in the context of &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo; projects has been meticulously documented and every step is detailed somewhere. Where possible, papers and methods are publicly available and &amp;lsquo;open access&amp;rsquo;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata201618&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FAIR Principles&lt;/a&gt; are, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_talk_to_me_or_my_son_ever_again&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t talk to me&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have the tendency to hoard and take note of every little idea, draft or file that was generated through the ✨process✨of a project just in case we have to &amp;rsquo;take a look back&amp;rsquo; and reflect on it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also a big fan of using diagrams to describe stuff in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./methods_slide_lshtm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Slide&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Slide from a presentation for the course &#39;Data Challenge&#39;, as part of my MSc programme. Map on the right is my own. Diagram on the left probably not.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My documentation problem comes down to my &amp;ldquo;personal&amp;rdquo; projects (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=pet%20project&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pet projects?&lt;/a&gt;). Over the years I have written code in R for several tools to process, scrap, or extract data. I have generated data visualizations (most terrible, some great) that are located &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; in the many virtual files I possess, but none of it has been publicly posted anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some fragments of code lost to time are not impressive (or at least I would not call them as such), but I always think of them whenever I am asked for examples of previous work I have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./map_covid_policy_peru.png&#34; alt=&#34;COVID-19 Policy Map of Peru&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. Evolution of the different public health measures and policies taken during the COVID-19 pandemic in Perú, Mar-Jun 2020. Made by me using the package gantrify, from Giorgio Comai &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have I done some very complex Shiny apps? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do I have a Shiny app I can share with the class? No :(.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ✨data collection process✨ to automate the extraction of bidding data from a collection of unstructured texts, tables, and images inside Discord chat servers for a World of Warcraft: Classic community took me about a dozen hours to refine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I have to show for it is a very simple graphic which I actually really like (the graphic does tell a story, for those who are a bit more familiar with its contents), but in retrospective it falls short when trying to convey the technical aspects behind the data collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./trend_cost_gdkp_items.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;WoW plot&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. Price evolution in GDKPs for two items in the game &#34;World of Warcraft: Classic&#34;. Discord Servers were selected for the US realm of Pagle, PvE, Alliance side from the list available at the “GDKP/SR Weekly Calendar” from the PPNN and compiled by @Polyadic. Only items sold are considered. Original dataset contains 316 unique items and 10,747 data points. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I process unstructured chat data containing multiple types of data? Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I explain to you how I did it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh, kind of? Let me open the code I did 8 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;jruizcabrejos&#34;&gt;jruizcabrejos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;personal&amp;rdquo; website is one of those &amp;ldquo;personal projects&amp;rdquo; that at some point existed, got abandoned, and had to be rebuilt over and over again, due to a lack of maintenance and proper documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the &lt;code&gt;jruizcabrejos&lt;/code&gt; &amp;rsquo;nickname&amp;rsquo; around 2015, and bought the .com domain at some point in 2018, shortly after having the talk with my supervisor about which &amp;lsquo;scholar/academic&amp;rsquo; name should I choose for my (first) publication(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It kind of felt like choosing an appropriate username for a MMORPG videogame. Would you rather be known as the level 50 Warrior named &lt;code&gt;Save&lt;/code&gt;? (one word, simple, elegant) Or as the level 50 Warrior known as &lt;code&gt;XxAnimeManga01xX&lt;/code&gt;? (many words, unhinged, based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, &amp;ldquo;Jorge Ruiz&amp;rdquo; is fairly common and I would like to keep my mother surname, so I ended up using &amp;ldquo;Jorge Ruiz-Cabrejos&amp;rdquo; or jruizcabrejos / J. Ruiz-Cabrejos for &lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2055-3396&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;most things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;actually-its-hello-world&#34;&gt;Actually, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Hello, World!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These posts are a good excuse for me to document my personal projects and publish somewhere all the &amp;ldquo;waste code&amp;rdquo; that I generate along the way, starting with this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the figures above (Fig.1, Fig.2 and Fig.3) took me longer than it took to write this post. So I guess, maybe, it is more of an ’indexing’ problem and not so much a ’lack of documentation’ problem what I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./meme_tiktok.png&#34; alt=&#34;My brain rot&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. &#34;If you see me one day uploading to my tiktok a blog of my day-to-day and saying stuff no one asked with 2 likes, 10 views and 0 comments, leave me alone. I am exactly where I want to be&#34; from @desorden-memetico on Instagram.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really helpful resources I used while building this website (and that I am 100% sure I will find myself looking back at them) are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://connorrothschild.github.io/v4/post/animate-hugo-academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://connorrothschild.github.io/v4/post/animate-hugo-academic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://matteocourthoud.github.io/post/website/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://matteocourthoud.github.io/post/website/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dsquintana.blog/create-an-academic-website-free-easy-2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.dsquintana.blog/create-an-academic-website-free-easy-2020/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nickballou.com/blog/custom-wowchemy/#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://nickballou.com/blog/custom-wowchemy/#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emilyzabor.com/tutorials/rmarkdown_websites_tutorial.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.emilyzabor.com/tutorials/rmarkdown_websites_tutorial.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some personal websites I looked at for inspiration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://theo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://theo.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nickballou.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://nickballou.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://matteocourthoud.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://matteocourthoud.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://djnavarro.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://djnavarro.net/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;Footnote&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;],I guess&amp;rdquo; in the title is a reference to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xuCn8ux2gbs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;amazing video from bill wurtz&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xuCn8ux2gbs?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
